Robert Hillyer Papers
Robert Hillyer Papers
- Outgoing correspondence
  - Folder 3 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 14 ALS, 2 TLS, 1 Typescript of a poem, and 2 newspaper clippings dated 1920-1921. These were written by Hillyer from shipboard en route to Denmark; from London; and Copenhagen to Hillyer's mother, Mrs. James Rankin Hillyer; in East Orange, New Jersey. These letters describe London, and Copenhagen at length and compare them to Paris. Hillyer's work as an American Fellow at the University of Copenhagen under the auspices of The American-Scandinavian Foundation is frequently mentioned as is his elaborate social life.
  - Folder 4 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of typescript Copies of the letters mentioned in folder 3.
  - Folder 5 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 2 Signed cards dated 1917. They were written from Paris to his sister, Mrs. Lillian Hillyer Marsh, and comment on the beauty of Paris.
  - Folder 6 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 1 ALS written from East Orange, New Jersey, by Robert Hillyer, as a child, to his brother Stanley, away at school. This Letter was written by Hillyer with his father guiding his hand and is referred to in an essay on Pomfret.
  - Folder 7 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 6 ALS, 2 signed cards, 5 signed notes, and 1 Telegram, dated 1953-1954. They are written from Greenwich, Connecticut and Newark, Delaware, to Mrs. Jeanne Duplaix Hillyer before and after her marriage to Hillyer.
  - Folder 8 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 4 xerox copies of 2 ALS and 2 TLS dated 1959-1961. They were written from Newark, Delaware, to Mr. Ray Bradbury in California. Hillyer is impressed with the control Bradbury has established over his material and compliments him on it. He also thanks Bradbury for his generous comments on Hillyer's poetry.
  - Folder 9 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 10 xerox copies of 9 ALS and 1 signed Card, dated 1954-1959. They are written from Newark, Delaware, to Mr. John Dos Passos near Baltimore, Maryland. Hillyer discusses the continuing power of Dos Passos writing and discusses several of his books. He also thanks Dos Passos for the unexpectedly praiseful criticism given by him of Hillyer's The Death of Captain Nemo.
  - Folder 10 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 52 ALS, 47 TLS, 2 Signed Cards, 8 Typescript copies of poems, and 1 Typescript quotation from a letter dated 1944-1961. Hillyer wrote these from California; Cambridge, Massachusetts; New York City; Old Greenwich, Connecticut; Gambier, Ohio; on board the Gloriana; and Newark, Delaware to Frank Garrison in Santa Barbara, California. Hillyers decision to retire from Harvard and his effort to devote his remaining years to writing, is traced over a period of four years. His life and attitudes during that time are clearly stated. These letters contain explanations of his decision to resume teaching and give details concerning the positions he held. Spread throughout the letters are explanations and expositions of Hillyer's social and political attitudes in addition to literary comments and analyses.
  - Folder 11 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 58 xerox copies of 25 ALS, 24 TLS, and 9 Signed Cards dated from 1946 to 1957; written from Greenwich, Connecticut; Beverly, Massachusetts, Gambier, Ohio, and Newark, Delaware, sent to Mr. and Mrs. Walter Marion Havighurst in Oxford, Ohio. Hillyer discusses his efforts at successful commercial writing at length. He often analyses his reasons for leaving his teaching career and reflects on his varied reactions to his new-found freedom from responsibility. The Havighurst's efforts at match-making for Hillyer result in a friendship. His lack of success as a commercial writer leads Hillyer to resume his teaching career; this decision is discussed. Throughout the correspondence Hillyer comments on his generally depressed and distracted state resulting from his homelessness and his desire to be taken care of.
  - Folder 12 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 2 xerox copies of 1 TLS and 1 ALS written from Cambridge, Massachusetts, to Stone Harbor, New Jersey, by Hillyer to Joseph Hergesheimer. These two letters contain an interesting discussion of the Shakespearean sonnets.
  - Folder 13 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 14 ALS, 14 TLS, 1 Signed Card, and 1 Typescript copy of first letter from Hillyer to Louis Kent, and 3 Typescript copies of poems by Kent dated 1945-1947. These letters were written from Stamford, Connecticut; Old Greenwich, Connecticut, and Bloomington, Indiana, to Louis Kent in Tuscaloosa, Alabama and Washington, D. C. Primary emphasis of this correspondence is the encouragement and criticism of Louis Kent, a totally unknown poet, whom Hillyer launched. Hillyer compares his own writing problems to those of the new author and succeeds in helping him win the Shelley Memorial Award. Publication of Kent's book, Declensions of the Air, results from his contacts with Louise Townsend Nicholls.
  - Folder 14 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of a Signed Card written from Newark, Delaware, to Oliver St. John Gogarty in New York accepting his invitation to meet Mrs. Jeanne Duplaix, the future Mrs. Robert Hillyer.
  - Folder 15 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 1 model TLS, and 18 carbons of same and 1 carbon TLS by Mrs. Hillyer. This was sent from Newark, Delaware, to London, England; New York City, New York; Boston, Massachusetts. All correspondence relates to permissions required to quote verse in Hillyer's projected book In Pursuit of Poetry.
  - Folder 16 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 1 ALS dated 1959, probably never sent. It was written at Newark, Delaware, to Gray Williams, Jr. of McGraw-Hill Book Company in New York City. This letter describes Hillyer's progress on his book In Pursuit of Poetry and estimates its length.
  - Folder 17 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 1 carbon of a TLS dated 1961. Written from Newark, Delaware, it was sent to Mr. Leon Wilson of McGraw-Hill Book Company, New York City. Hillyer briefly discusses the contract for his projected, never-finished memoirs. He also explains the general theme of the memoirs and attaches a "Prolegomenon for a book of reminiscences of Robert Hillyer" which gives a twelve-section outline of Hillyer's plan for the book.
  - Folder 18 (Box 7)
    Miscellaneous outgoing correspondence consists of three notes in Hillyer's hand. They are drafts of messages. Correspondent unidentified.
- General correspondence
  - Miscellaneous letters, referring to sale of Hillyer's Papers and Library (Box 8)
    Consists of 4 TLS, 6 ALS written from Newark, Delaware, to Austin, Texas; Charlottesville, Virginia, and Carbondale, Illinois. Several inquiries are answered and Mrs. Hillyer's plans for creating a presentation catalogue of the collection are mentioned.
  - Incoming correspondence, Aa-Kz (Box 8)
    Consists of 75 letters, primarily fan mail.
  - Incoming correspondence, La-Zz, 2 folders (Box 8)
    Consists of 138 letters, primarily fan mail.
  - Incoming unidentifiable correspondence (Box 8)
    Consists of 58 letters signed with prename only or with unidentifiable surnames, primarily fan mail.
- Manuscripts
  - Manuscript of Completed Poems (Box 8)
    Contains 24 holograph pages of poems, each one signed and dated. Book is dated 1943 but poems are dated 1917 and 1918. No corrections or annotations. Many of the poems are sonnets and some have to do with war ("War Fugue" for example).
  - Manuscript of Practice Notebook for writing prose (Box 9)
    Contains 12 holograph pages of corrected prose and 3 pages of corrected poetry. Prose seems to be beginning of autobiographical story.
  - Manuscript of Practice Notebook for writing poetry (Box 9)
    Contains 10 holograph pages of corrected poetry.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Prose Draft (Box 9)
    Contains 5 holograph pages corrected prose. This is a draft for a nostalgic reminiscence of pre-World War I Days.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Prose Draft (Box 9)
    Contains 11 holograph pages of corrected prose. This is an elaborate draft for a reminiscent article about Hillyer's Harvard friends, among them John Dos Passos, Dillywyn Parish, Anne Parish, Lowell Downes, Russell Jackson, Scofield Thayer and John Sibley Watson.
  - Manuscript of Prose Draft on poetry and corrected drafts of poems (Box 9)
    Contains 31 holograph pages of prose and poetry drafts. Prose seems to be draft for article or chapter on a definition of poetry; poems are mainly short lyrics.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Drafts (Box 9)
    Contains 21 holograph pages of alternating prose and poetry drafts, most are fragmentary. Prose drafts contain two fragmentary fiction pieces and poetry contains humorous poem in heroic couplets.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Prose and Poetry Drafts (Box 9)
    Contains 17 holograph pages. The major prose fragment is a story of a reunion in France between Hillyer and a friend.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Drafts of poetry and prose (Box 9)
    Contains 25 holograph pages. There is a long autobiographical prose fragment based on Hillyer's friendship with Marguerite Dumaine and family; poetry drafts contain early versions of poem for Hillyer's granddaughter and other poems.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Poetry, Fiction and Essay Draft (Box 9)
    Contains 45 holograph pages of corrected fragments. There are 3 versions of a narrative poem, several drafts of poems in the style of Verlaine, a few paragraphs of a short story, a long draft of a review of Richard Hovey's biography, and many drafts of poems.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Poetry Drafts (Box 9)
    Contains 78 holograph pages of corrected poetry drafts. There is one prose fragment about an experience in France; the rest of the manuscript contains many drafts of various poems.
  - Manuscript of Corrected Drafts of poetry (Box 9)
    Contains 24 holograph pages of poetry drafts.
  - Manuscript of Completed Poems (Box 9)
    Contains 14 holograph pages of dated, final versions of several poems. Among the poems included here are "Chanson Triste," "Postlude," "The PhD's," " The Little Music," and "Miss Harvey"; author's comments appear frequently.
  - Manuscripts of corrected poetry drafts (Box 9)
    22 holograph pages in ink. There are several fragments of poems and 2 fairly long drafts.
  - Manuscripts of corrected prose and poetry drafts (Box 9)
    Contains 21 holograph pages. Several poetry drafts precede and follow a long draft of author's The Pursuit of Poetry, published by Marshall College, Huntington, West Virginia, which served as base for In Pursuit of Poetry.
  - Manuscripts of poetry drafts (Box 9)
    Contains 48 holograph pages of which 9 are loose sheets laid in.
  - Manuscript of corrected copy of fiction article (Box 10)
    Contains 78 holograph pages of corrected fiction. There are several drafts of poems interspersed.
  - Manuscript of corrected draft of prose (Box 10)
    Contains 66 holograph pages of corrected prose.
  - Manuscript of corrected draft of prose (Box 10)
    Contains 5 1/4 holograph pages. This is a fragment of the introduction of the textbook version of First Principles of Verse.
  - Manuscript consists of corrected drafts of prose and poetry (Box 10)
    Contains 57 holograph pages. This contains a complete draft of a review of Years and Hours of Emily Dickinson by Leyda, a partial draft of a review of The Letters and Epigrams of Sir John Harrington by Norman Egbert McClure, a partial draft of a review of David Daiches' Critical History of English Literature, and a complete draft of The Owl Hoots Twice at Catfish Bend by Ben Lucien Burman; there are also several poetry drafts.
  - Manuscript of corrected review of a book of poetry by John Masefield. (Box 10)
  - Manuscript of corrected draft of reminiscences (Box 10)
    Contains reminiscences of Harvard, poet's father and extends through his acquaintance with Kahlil Gibran, Arthur Machen, Cuthbert Wright, John Dos Passos, Frederick van den Arend, and others.
  - Typescript copies of articles from the New York Times Book Review "Speaking of Books" section. (Box 10)
  - Typescript of Farrago. (Box 10)
  - Typescript copy of Miss Jennie with holograph marginal comment by Gene Fowler. (Box 10)
  - Typescript copies of Sophia's Villa. (Box 10)
  - Typescripts of various poems (Box 10)
    Academic Spring
    A Change of Climate
    After Verlaine A Memory
    A Popular English Novel
    A Reflection A Song
    At the Debutantes' Ball
    At the Garden Club
    A Valentine
    Candor in Autumn Cock-of-the-Wind Evening Breeze Four Sonnets 1478
    Intermezzo
    June Bridal
    Late Summer Sadness
    Lermontov of Pushkin
    Like flecks of flame bright leaves are earthward twirling Many Happy Returns, My Dear Fellow
    Mockingbird Singing by Night
    Most freed from time of all time's intervals
    Night Wind
    Nocturne
    November Nocturne Now
    Parnassus - 1935
    Promenade in a Capital of the Period
    Remembering the Master
    Revenant
    Robert from Robert
    Somnolent Summer Afternoon
    Sonnet
    Still Life
    The Descendant
    The Eternal Return
    The Home Place The Inscription The Laggard
    The Moment
    The Searchlight
    The Scenic Railway
    The Suspended Moment
    The Swirl
    The Translation The Two
    The Girl in the Garden
    The Wild Philosophers
    Through the Insomnious Night
    Under the Oak Winter Warmth
    Word Game
  - Typescripts of various poems (Box 10)
    A Bookman's Poem for Christmas
    Adam Lay I-Bowndyn
    Against my Contemporaries
    An Acquisition
    Bayeux Tapestry
    Before the Wreckers Come
    Caedmon
    Coda
    Dusk on the Delaware
    Dusk on the Chesapeake
    E. D. (1886- )
    Fantasia
    Foredoomed
    Hazelwood
    Hymn for Thanksgiving Day
    It is not well to be weatherwise
    Juvenilia Retrieved
    More than Sky-High
    Mrs. Moran New England Epitaph
    Nocturne in a Minor Key
    One Kind of Colloquy
    On the Narrow Brink of Dawn
    Perhaps an Elegy
    Prelude
    Rough Winds do shake the darling buds of May
    Sapphic Ode
    Song
    Summer Evening
    Summer Night
    The Bitter Withy
    The Bobwhite
    The Cardinal Flower
    The Chamber of Commerce
    The Cherry-Tree Carol
    The Dark Garden
    The Encounter
    The Garden on the Moors
    The Hammock in the Orchard
    The House
    The Hunting Season
    The Marauders
    The Misses Adams
    The Scar
    The Song of Jeptha's Daughter
    The Star-Tree Carol
    The Storke
    The Translation
    The Wayfarers
    Three Guesses
    To My Granddaughter Elizabeth
    Tourists in a New England Graveyard
    With trembling fingers did we weave
    Tryste Noel
    Voyage to the Island
  - Typescript copies of reviews by Robert Hillyer (Box 11)
    Allegory and Suggestion
    A New Study of Shakespeare
    Ancient Egypt
    A Poet Young and Old
    Armadas in Miniature
    Arthur Machen
    Through the Gates of Hercules
    Bolts of Memory, New Poems by Emily Dickinson
    Ancestors' Brocades, The Literary Debut of Emily Dickinson
    Collected Poems
    Crabbed Age and Youth
    Danish Poetry of the Last Century
    Education Unvisited
    Egyptian Civilization Father Tabb
    Five American Poets
    My Incomparable Queen
    Nine Books of Verse
    On Reading Verse Aloud
    Pharaoh Akhnaton
    Poets' People
    Recent Poetry
    Reminiscences of Arthur Machen
    Shelley, The Man and the Poet
    T'ao the Hermit: Six poems by T'ao Ch'ien
    The Ancient East
    The Decline of Gusto
    The Gate of Silence
    A Garland about Me
    The Dark Sister
    The Letters of John Keats
    The Life and Times of Tut-Ankh-Amen
    The Merry Songs of Peace
    The Poems of Charles Cotton
    The Poetic Nuisance
    The Season of Flesh
    Verbiage, Diction, Poetry What God Has Joined Together: An Essay on Love
  - Typescript copy of untitled story (Box 11)
  - Typescript copy of a fictional letter (Box 11)
  - Typescript copies of early prose articles as follows (Box 11)
    Commencement Four Epigrams
    Untitled Story
    Let's Be Informal (Play)
    Mysterious Ways Seven Days and After
    Solitude in Literature
    The Hundredth Grave
    The Three Brothers
    The Travellers
  - Corrected typescript of "Nocturne in a Minor Key" (Box 11)
  - Typescript copy of verse written as a Harvard undergraduate. (Box 11)
  - Typescript copy of Spanish translation of poetry by Hillyer (Box 11)
  - Typescript and several holograph drafts of "Summer Evening" (Box 11)
  - Typescript and several holograph drafts of "The Lifeboat" (Box 11)
  - Typescript copies of "Ode on the Peace" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript with holograph drafts of "This is the Moment" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "A Parting" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "Sonnet" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "The Tapestry" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of untitled poems (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "The Scar" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "Perhaps an Elegy" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "The Ivory Tower" (Box 11)
  - Corrected typescript of "The Two" (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of holograph drafts of untitled poems (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of holograph drafts of untitled poems (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of holograph drafts of untitled poems (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of miscellaneous holograph drafts of untitled poems (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of holograph drafts of "The Muffled Gong" (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of holograph drafts of "But I by backward steps would move" (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of completed version of "A Memory," holograph, signed (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of beginning of poem "Requiem for Captain Nemo," holograph, signed (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of poem to Franklin Delano Roosevelt, holograph, signed (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of three holograph lyric poems, signed (Box 11)
  - Childhood schoolwork in holograph, signed (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of two holograph early poems, signed (Box 11)
  - Typescript copies of poems from The Suburb by the Sea (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of corrected holograph draft of The Death of Captain Nemo (Box 11)
  - Typescript copy of The Death of Captain Nemo (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: Lyrics and Shorter Poems I (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: The Death of Captain Nemo (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: Lyrics and Shorter Poems II (Box 11)
  - Typescript of "E. A. Robinson and His Tristram" (Box 11)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: Variations on a Theme - Sonnets, Pastorals, Prothalamion (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: The Gates of the Compass (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: Letters (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: Lyrics and Shorter Poems III (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of setting copy of Collected Poems: Index of First Lines (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of plate proofs of a portion of Collected Poems (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of plate proofs of Collected Poems (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of author's first proof of Collected Poems (Box 12)
  - Manuscript of page proofs of Collected Poems (Box 12)
  - Unbound copy of Collected Poems (Box 12)
  - Typescript and mimeographed copies of serious prose articles (Box 13)
    Untitled reminiscence about East Orange, New Jersey
    My Civil War
    Emily Dickinson
    In Defense of Light Verse
    Poetry at Christmas
    Robert Bridges and the Testament of Beauty
    The Crisis in American Poetry
    The Metaphorical Age
    The Records of the Pre-Deluge of the Caucasus Isthmus
  - Typescript copies of prose articles (Box 13)
    Accept Your Limitations
    A Dinner in the Slums
    A Country House at Night
    A Memorial to Heroes
    Conversation Piece
    High Tea at Mrs. Dumaine's
    James Elijah
    John the Baptist
    Make a Mistake
    Midnight at the Royal Palace
    Monument
    Mr. Copeland's Memoirs
    My Heart for Hostage (Synopsis)
    Never Go Back
    The Bones of Carl Devens
    The Bostonian's Return
    The Double Countess
    The Gargoyles
    The Initial Case
    The Island
    The Knotted Thread
    The Portrait of Jacqueline
    The Reservoir
    The Sunflowers
    The Uneventful Crossing
    This is My Desk, My Pen, My Paper, My Ink
    Wait and See
    Why Scoff at Kings
    Wreckers' Island
  - Manuscript of Galley Proof of In Pursuit of Poetry (Box 13)
  - Printed Copy of The Pursuit of Poetry (Box 13)
  - Typescript of reminiscences concerning the supernatural (Box 13)
  - Typescript of reminiscences of early childhood (Box 13)
  - Typescript of reminiscences of Harvard classmates (Box 13)
  - Typescript and carbon copy of article on Roger Sessions (Box 13)
  - Typescript copy of "Thoughts on Approaching Harvard University" by G. S. Terry (Box 13)
  - Typescript copies of various addresses by Hillyer (Box 13)
  - Manuscript and final typescript of three holograph drafts of Centennial Lecture on Robert Burns delivered at Library of Congress January 25, 1959 (Box 13)
  - Manuscripts of outlines of readings given in Brown Hall, University of Delaware, 1953-1959 (Box 13)
  - Manuscripts of miscellaneous outlines of poetry readings. (Box 13)
  - Manuscript of outline for address to students at Kenyon College, 1952 (Box 13)
  - Typescript outlines of poetry readings for radio and television (Box 13)
  - Manuscripts of Hillyer's college theme papers (Box 13)
  - Manuscripts of miscellaneous and fragmentary manuscripts (Box 13)
  - Typescript lecture outline on T. S. Eliot, undated (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of holograph lecture outline for English 41 - English 478 - Kenyon College, 1948 (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of preparation notebook for English 34 - Kenyon College, 1948 (Box 14)
  - Grade Notebook from University of Delaware, 1958-1959 (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of preparation notebook for Modern Poetry Class, undated (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of preparation notebook for English 417 at University of Delaware, 1958 (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of class outline and plan for English 64, 1948-1949 (Box 14)
  - Manuscripts of unidentified musical score (Liszt) (Box 14)
  - Manuscripts of original music by Robert Hillyer (Box 14)
    First Prelude
    Second Prelude
  - Copies of published songs, using poetry by Hillyer (Box 14)
    Early in the Morning
    For He is Risen
    Morning in Paris
    O Make Our Hearts to Blossom
    Twentieth Century
  - Minutes of English Department meetings, University of Delaware, December 15, 1954; May 4, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Xerox copies of poems set to music (Box 14)
    April Morning
    At Anchor
    Autumn Mooring
    Be Calm, 0 Soul So Often Tried
    Christmas Eve
    Folk Song: Elegy Forever
    Goodnight with Lullaby
    Here is My Book
    Hickory Hill
    Home Port
    Julia's Room
    Lullaby
    Moo!
    Original Sin
    Rendez-vous
    Serenade
    Seven Epigrams
    Song from Ancient Egypt
    So Soft in the Hemlock Wood
    The Anchor
    The Dance will end at Midnight
    The Ironwood Tree
    The Leaf
    The Old Love Letter
    The Swan
    The Untended Field
    Three Pastorals
    Uneventful Return
    Young Lovers in Wartime
  - Manuscripts consisting of musical setting of Hillyer's The Garden of Artemis (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous musical material (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous
  - Genealogical record of Robert S. Hillyer (Box 15)
  - Official papers pertaining to Hillyer (Box 15)
  - Tearsheets of Hillyer articles appearing in the New York Times (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of magazines and prose stories (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of magazines and prose stories (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of reviews by Hillyer (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of articles concerning The Bollingen Award (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of poetry (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of review of Sonnets and Lyrics (Box 16)
  - Tearsheets of review of The Five Books of Youth (Box 16)